VIJAY SHANKER KUMAR

5/29, Kalpana | Sector 5, Vaishali, | Ghaziabad, 201010 (UP), India. Cell No- +91 9891558062 Email-vijay7202@yahoo.com

System/Network Engineer

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

The System/Network Engineer role is to manage server, security, network connection, storage device and computer software systems, to ensure high availability and security of the supported business applications.

IT Professional with 10+ years experience in System/Network Engineer, including, analyzing, designing, installing, maintaining, hardware, software, peripherals, and networks.

EDUCATION QUALIFICATION

- MCA in Computer Science from Annamalai University, 2018-19.
- M.Sc Computer Science from Annamalai University, 2017-18.
- PGDCA from Annamalai University, 2016-17.
- Bachelor's degree in Mathematics from Alagappa University, Karaikudi, Tamil Nadu.
- B.E. (Computer Science) Section-B from AMIE India.
- Intermediate (12th) Examination in Science from Bihar Intermediate Council, Patna.
- BSE (10th) passed from Bihar School Examination Board, Patna in 1986.

PROFESSINOL QUALIFICATION:

- Microsoft Certified Professional Windows Server (MCP) in 2005.
- 'O' LEVEL (From New Delhi) DOEACC in 2003.
- CCNA(Cisco Certified Network Associate) in 2007.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Manage physical servers with Windows Server 2000,2003,2008,2012,2016
- Windows 2008/2012/2016 Server knowledge inc Active Directory / Group Policies / DNS
- Installation, Administration & Troubleshooting of Active Directory Services (ADS),
- Organization Unit (OU) and Group Policy.
- Manage Active Directory, Domain Name System, Windows Internet Naming Service.
- Manage end user accounts, permission access right and storage allocations in accordance with best practice, Shell Scripting Under Windows.
- IIS 7.0 Administration, Installation and Maintains of Proxy server.
- ISA 2000/2006/2010, Exchange Server 2007/2010/2013, SQL Server 2005/2008/2012.
- Deep Knowledge on Server Roles DNS, DHCP, File Server.
- HP, IBM, Dell, Blade Servers, and desktops, laptops, Cisco Routers & Switches, Fortinet firewall, & Watch Guard firewalls.
- Responsible for LAN/WAN network communications, operations, hardware and application software.
- TCPIP networking / LAN / WAN / WIFI
- Next Generation Firewalls VPN / Client VPN / IP routing / Troubleshooting / Maintenance / Support / Security/Access polices
- AWS knowledge specifically VPC / Workspaces / EC2 / Terra form
- Routing Protocols TCP/IP, IPX/SPX, PPP, Ethernet, Fast Ethernet, Token Ring, SMTP/POP3/IMAP, FTP, Telnet, SSH, SNMP, WINS, DHCP, DNS TCP/IP, VPN, bridges and switches, OSI model and fiber optic technology. Network Troubleshooting.

- Coordinated with other teams to support network hardware such as firewalls, load balance and switches and storage hardware.
- Server hardware planning & implementation, troubleshooting and maintenance.
- Configuring networked workstations.
- Network and server support.
- Configure the router and switches.
- Configure the outlook and managing email server.
- Installation of network printer.
- Implemented WI-fi set up with SSID and WAP2 security.
- Installation of OS- MS Windows (XP,7,8.1,10,Linux.,Ubuntu14.4.)
- Symantec Endpoint 12.1, Mozy Pro Backup, Quick Book Account Software.
- MS Office 2003/2007/2010/2013/2016, Knowledge of Office 365.
- Troubleshooting of Wintel platform based laptop/desktop.
- Installation & Troubleshooting of CCTV Camera.
- Knowledge of 24/7 implementation and management of information technology support operations to include help desk, Call-in support and work priority management.

WORK EXPERIENCE

(1) Apeejay Group, Gr Noida. Designation: System Admin

December 2005 - PRESENT

- Managed systems configuration and maintenance, troubleshooting, system and network security with Cyber Trust, security, and program management, network monitoring and performance tuning, applications.
- Provided design, implementation, Architect, installed and maintained administration and support of Windows Server 2008/2012/2016, Active Directory.
- Managed the Help desk & Desktop Support team which supported Windows 9.X, 2000, XP,
 Vista and Windows 7 along with the MS-Office including mail services.
- Investigated new technologies, software, patches, and security packages, which will improve system performance and systems administration procedures.
- Installed and configured Migrated Exchange 2000 to 2003, Exchange client configuration using Microsoft Office Outlook.
- Maintenance of Microsoft Office Outlook Web Access and Maintenance of Microsoft Office Outlook E-mail, Calendaring & Scheduling. Troubleshooting of Microsoft Office Outlook database & structure problems.
- Windows Server 2003, 2008 R2 installation, deployments, troubleshooting and automation.
- Windows Server 2008 Hyper V vitalization configuration for servers.
- Monitor ticketing system for new tickets and work items. Update existing tickets. Maintain hardware inventory control in ticketing system.
- Proactively monitor systems health by physically inspecting environment and utilizing provided tools such as SCOM.
- Troubleshoot server hardware and software issues and escalate accordingly.
- Supported LAN/WAN, Windows Server 2003 Active Directory infrastructure in 5 locations consisting of over 300 end-users, 8+ physical servers, and 275+ workstations using Windows XP Pro, Vista, windows7, and Windows10 with 15+ network printers.

- Concurrently responsible for maintaining security and availability of data center supporting multiple production environments.
- Windows Server 2008, upgrading 250+ PCs from Windows XP & 7 to Windows 10, while also upgrading from MS Office 2003, 2007 to MS Office 2010,2013,2016.
- Provided production level support for Windows Server 2003, 2008,2012, Windows 7 and MS Office 2010/2013/2016.
- Maintained availability of LAN/WAN resources in multi domain, Microsoft Windows 2003 Server, Active Directory Environment.

(2) Solar Print Process Pvt. Ltd. New Delhi. India Designation: Network Engineer

May 2002 - Nov 2005

- Network Engineer responsible for supporting, development and production in a windows /Linux/ MAC are environment. Responsible for infrastructure, hardware support and implementation.
- Installed new IBM X3400/X226/X220 set to use ldap, nfs, cifs on non standard network.
- Implemented new DNS and DHCP. Setup new local backup system.
- Installed and Upgraded My SQL servers.
- Analyses LAN to determine whatever the major problems and improvements needed to be made to the network infrastructure.

(3) Front line Solution HCL-HP Ltd, Noida. (OJT) Technical Support Engineer

Feb 1997 – April 2002

- Responsible of day-to-day Network and technical problems of computer. The work of installation and configuration relating to WIN NT server terminals and providing them mainframe connectivity, knowledge of client server, novel network type of networking architecture. Knowledge of data communication over local and wide area networks. Analyses of Customer LAN to determine network Performance problems provide solution and documentation.
- Worked as Trainee at HCL- HP Ltd., NOIDA as a Customer Support Engineer. As a trainee, I was given the responsibility of considering day-to-day network and technical problems that generally occur in terminals as well as in network-lines/cables. The work was basically related to installation and configuration of terminals and providing them mainframe connectivity.

PERSONAL DETAILS:

Date of Birth	2 nd February, 1972
Marital Status	Married
Sex	Male
Nationality	Indian
Language proficiency	English, Hindi

DECLARATION:

I hereby declare that the above given information are true to the best of my knowledge and belief.

Date: (VIJAY SHANKER KUMAR)